ALOY: For your punishment they'll exile you from the werak?
INATUT: From warmth.
INATUT: March me up the slopes of the Cloud-Shear.
Leave me stripped and exposed.
ALOY: That's awful.
INATUT: If I survive, the land has absolved me.
INATUT: That's the law. It must be accepted.
ALOY: Still awful.
INATUT: I'm not stupid, I don't like my chances either.
INATUT: I can't fight a mountain.
ALOY: I'll be honest, you haven't got a good defence, Inatut.
INATUT: I've heard that one before.
ALOY: Where did the fight happen?
INATUT: A clearing, just outside the Carja outlander's camp.
INATUT: You should talk to them, they wouldn't hear me out.
They say no-one else could have been there, other than me and the dead man.
The Shaman consulted the signs in the snow and agreed.
ALOY: I'll see what I can find out and I'll be back.
INATUT: I'll be here. What else am I gonna do?
Until the horn gives a call for my exile.
ALOY: For what you did another Banuk has been sentenced to certain death.
What about his song?
RUKUL: That's why you followed us?
For that punch-drunk idiot Inatut.
[horn blares in the distance]
RUKUL: Fate is sharp today.
They've already led him out to face his exile.
Let's see who the cold claims first.
ALOY: I need to go after Inatut.
ALOY: But I should find some more evidence first.
Trophies.
Newer than the rest.
It must have belonged to Ruwas.
So it was a Carja soldier's.
Not that it's any excuse.
Did they keep any clothes from their victims?
This Carja gear's not warm.
But if Inatut's naked on a snowfield, he'll take what he gets.
Okay, time to get moving.
There!
It's a start!
Kind of place you'd take someone if you wanted to lose them forever.
I'm not getting up that frozen waterfall.
Maybe along the sides?
Now's my chance.
Low and quiet does it.
Chill almost feels like sunburn.
Inatut? INATUT!
Maybe he found shelter?
I hope he found shelter.
Behind the rock.
INATUT: The Nora girl?
INATUT: Is it really you, or has the bone chill got through my skull?
ALOY: I found the real killers.
ALOY: No-one else has to die because of this.
ALOY: Take these.
INATUT: A dead Carja's clothes? Haven't I been beaten down enough?
INATUT: But I won't argue.
INATUT: Swear I thought I saw my ancestors.
INATUT: They said "Weren't surprised you ended up here."
ALOY: Better hurry — machines!
INATUT: Now that was a fight!
ALOY: Your trial's over. It was other Banuk who killed that man.
ALOY: Killed him because he was Carja.
INATUT: You know why I took the first swing at him?
INATUT: He challenged the honour of the Banuk.
INATUT: The honour.
INATUT: That's what I thought.
ALOY: Come on, let's get you back.
INATUT: Once I'm off the mountain, I'll find my own way.
INATUT: I need to think.
INATUT: It's not something I'm used to.
INATUT: Who knows what could happen?
ALOY: I'll see you in town, then.
ALOY: You'd better make it, alright?
INATUT: I give my pledge.
ALOY: So by Banuk law if Inatut survives he's forgiven.
But I want to prove to his chieftain that he wasn't guilty in the first place.
Just like in the Cauldron.
All of the winters coming at once.
BANUK: How can we expect any Shaman to fill the footprints Ourea left behind?
BANUK: The hunting party said the Rockbreaker burst from the ice
just in front of them. They're lucky to be alive.
BANUK: Some say the Tallneck at the Frostfigures is
some sort of spiritual site. That's just a dead machine.
BANUK: Some days it seems like the blue light has no hold any more.
ALOY: Inatut told you the truth.
This is the headdress stolen from the murdered man.
You'll find more in a ravine north and west of here.
Along with the bodies of the killers.
AUJAK: The exile still served its purpose.
AUJAK: He was guilty of our suspicion.
Fate has fallen like snow, and should Inatut return he will be absolved.
ALOY: You can't be serious!
INATUT: He speaks for the werak my Nora friend.
KOPILAI: You look ridiculous.
KOPILAI: If you would return to my werak, you will behave as a Banuk does.
INATUT: How does a Banuk behave my chieftain?
INATUT: Like I did, accepting a sentence for a crime he did not commit?
Or those others who killed in cold blood
for crimes that their Carja victims did not?
I think what I wear will not make me more or less of a Banuk.
KOPILAI: For his own sake it would be wise for him to think less, "Nora friend".
ALOY: I'll talk to him, but not for you.
INATUT: I defied my chieftains will, spurned my werak.
ALOY: How are you feeling?
INATUT: As if I've been pounded in the guts.
INATUT: I could just keep walking, but…
INATUT: …when my anger has thawed it will leave me with nothing.
INATUT: Where else would I go?
ALOY: There's so much more out there, beyond your borders and laws.
ALOY: It won't be easy but I know you can roll with the hits.
INATUT: But without a werak?
To be a Banuk alone, what would I be fighting for?
ALOY: How about yourself Inatut? You just did it.
INATUT: Huh. I am Inatut who fights for himself.
INATUT: There's a good echo to it,
and so many unknown mountaintops to shout it from!
ALOY: You can decide for yourself what it means to be a Banuk.
ALOY: It might not be what the chieftain and the Shaman tell you.
INATUT: I'm better with decisions like do I start with the left or the right?
ALOY: There is more to you than your fists, Inatut.
ALOY: That's why I believed you.
INATUT: It was my chieftain who taught me honesty.
INATUT: Said "A Banuk should not be treacherous
when the ice is treacherous enough."
ALOY: You survived exile, I bet that doesn't happen much.
INATUT: I've only heard of it in legends.
ALOY: You earned your place in the werak Inatut, make them earn you back.
INATUT: Of all my fights, this is the first time I beat death.
INATUT: I'll sit with my bruises for a time, then talk with her again.
INATUT: As for you Nora girl, will you accept this gift?
INATUT: A little scrawny weighed against the great boon you gave me, but…
ALOY: I'm honoured. Thank you, Inatut.
BANUK: Can't be, he'd be older than the first song by now.
FURAHNI: Huntress. We should thank you for finding the truth in this sorry mess.
Your Banuk came to us to explain what happened,
wearing a long dead Carja's garb.
The priest thought he was having a religious vision.
ALOY: I have brought back the stolen headdress too.
ALOY: The inscription inside said it was a soldier's?
FURAHNI: An heirloom, handed down to Ruwas.
FURAHNI: His father gave his life to help liberate Meridian.
FURAHNI: He was no Red Raider.
ALOY: What a waste!
FURAHNI: Like I said, a sorry mess.
FURAHNI: Well, we'll be returning to the Sundom. May you also go in light.
CARJA: The Sun-King's grown too soft. Too much Oseram influence in the palace.
BANUK: We've no time to host outsiders.
BANUK: I'll give this to the Oseram. Whatever they do, they do it with passion.
KOPILAI: There was an old Banuk tradition
to determine who had the strongest will.
KOPILAI: Some parts of Ban-Ur still use it.
KOPILAI: You take a hot coal in your fist,
and then hold it until you must plunge it into the snow.
KOPILAI: There were many warriors in those days
with a strong will and a ruined hand.
KOPILAI: I should have dropped the coal.
KOPILAI: Do you understand?
INATUT: Uh, I'm trying, my chieftain.
KOPILAI: I hewed to tradition
even though I was certain you did not commit the crime.
KOPILAI: I was wrong.
KOPILAI: You should not have to fight
for the werak's honour without knowing that.
INATUT: I've only heard my chieftain apologise once before.
INATUT: And that was to the old chieftain on the end of her spear.
ALOY: I think you got the better deal then.
I'd say look after yourself, but…
INATUT: Careful doesn't come naturally to me, I know.
BANUK: We should not pile his Father's guilt onto
the new Carja king's shoulders. These are different times.
BANUK: A hunt gone sour is no one's fault but the hunters'.
INATUT: There I was, atop the Cloud-Shear, the blizzard raining blows upon me.
INATUT: Back to back with the Nora warrior,
as the machines closed in, howling for blood.
INATUT: My hands were stiff as frozen branches,
still I raised my spear and howled back.
INATUT: Blood pounding, fire just flashing before my eyes in the white.
INATUT: As metal closed around us, I struck out, chipped the jaws of death.
INATUT: Each hit blasted me like thunder.
INATUT: How many could I stand for myself and my ally?
BANUK: But some say your tales are the stuff of campfires, Inatut.
INATUT: Who does? I'll fight them all!
ALOY: It all happened pretty much like he said.
ALOY: I know, I was there.
INATUT: And if she hadn't been, I'd be up there still.
INATUT: She did most of the work.
INATUT: It's true, I cheated an exile's fate.
INATUT: But I won't cheat you of your place in this tale.
INATUT: It's a slight tale compared to your own.
ALOY: It's not the length of the tale that matters, Inatut.
ALOY: I'm glad to have been a part of yours.
BANUK: Don't forget the Mad Sun-King's cruelty survives him, even if we can trust Meridian…
[horn blares]
We need to be somewhere else, yah!
Low and quiet does it.
I can feel the ground softening up.
That alarm will wake up the whole camp, and more besides.
BANDIT: You hear that?
ALOY: I'm not here.
BANDIT: See her up there!
ALOY: Looks like I'm clear.
ALOY: I can't spare the weight.
ALOY: What have they taken prisoners for?
ALOY: Nothing good.
ALOY: You're coming with me.
ALOY: Let's get you out of there.
BANDIT: Die, die!
NORA: Wild as beasts,
it's like the Metal Devil is whispering to them, corrupting them.
ALOY: Got too much already.
NORA: We will fight the corruption, 'til the last of us has fallen.